<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter, written by that famous and faithful minister of Christ Mr John Livingstoun unto his parishoners of Ancram in Scotland, dated Rotterdam October 7. 1671.</title>
            <author>Livingston, John, 1603-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48760</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216776</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828497</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828497</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32925</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48760)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32925)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1914:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter, written by that famous and faithful minister of Christ Mr John Livingstoun unto his parishoners of Ancram in Scotland, dated Rotterdam October 7. 1671.</title>
                  <author>Livingston, John, 1603-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Mr Livingston's letter to his parishoners of Ancram.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English letters --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32925:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> LETTER, Written by that famous and faithful Miniſter of Chriſt M<hi rend="sup">R</hi> JOHN LIVINGSTOUN, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto his Pariſhoners of</hi> ANCRAM in SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dated</hi> ROTTERDAM October 7. 1671.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32925:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32925:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:32925:3"/>
            <head>M<hi rend="sup">R</hi> LIVINGSTOUN'S Letter to his Pariſhoners of <hi>Ancram.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>VVell beloved in the Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> cannot excuſe my long ſilence. I have a woful lazie diſpoſition, and indiſpoſition for writing; yea, I judge any thing I write, is ſcarſe worthie that any ſhould look on, or read; beſides that my ſlow and ſhaking hand is ſome hinderance to me: Yet when I conſider, that I have an account to make for you to the great Shepheard, as having laboured amongſt you in the miniſtrie of this Word ſome four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Years; and now after neerby nine years baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment age and infirmities creep on, and through a conſtant pain of the gravel I have much ado once a week, on the Lords Day, to go a very ſhort way to the publick Worſhip; ſo as there is no great proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, I can ſee your face in this life; and it is moſt fitting for me, to ſet my face forward toward my laſt reckoning. I thought I behooved, in a manner, to make unto you my <hi>Teſtament,</hi> and open my minde concerning my ſelf, concerning you, and concerning the preſent poſtour of affairs in that <hi>Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the entrie, notwithſtanding of all the ſad things, that have fallen out of late, I would put you in minde of the many good dayes we have ſeen to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, both of Sabbath Dayes and ſolemne Communion Dayes, wherein we ſaw the Lords Power and his Grace in his Sanctuary; that in remembrance thereof we may exalt his Name together; and know that though he cauſe grief, yet he will have compaſſion, according to the multitude of his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: ye may eaſily diſcerne what a difference is between thoſe dayes, and ſuch as ye now ſee; and what an evil and bitter thing it is, that by our not improving of thoſe dayes, we have provoked him to hide his face, and ſend ſuch an inundation of matchleſs Apoſtacy, Perjurie, Perſecution, Profani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Atheiſm; yea Darkneſs, Diſtractions, and Deſpondency amongſt his own, in all which we may yet expect he is waiting to be gracious, and will be exalted that he may have mercy upon us.</p>
            <p>I. For my part, I have peace in regard of theſe particulars,
<list>
                  <item>1. That not only ſince my entrie into the Miniſtrie, but even from my infancy, the Lord was pleaſed to lead me to an averſion from Prelacy, a ſtinted Liturgie, the Ceremonies and other Corruptions of that time; and that in my Miniſtrie, both in <hi>Irland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> I joined with thoſe, who were ſtreight in the Cauſe of God, and teſtified againſt theſe evils: that I joined in the National Covenant and Solemn League and Covenant, and other parts of the work of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32925:3"/>Reformation, that was carried on in the Year 1638. and thereafter, as being aſſured that the Lord did then, does yet, and will ever approve of that work and the proſecution thereof.</item>
                  <item>2. That I came to <hi>Ancram,</hi> not out of any worldly end, but from a deſire to do ſervice to God, and to the Souls of his People; and had thereto the Lords call by your invitation, and the conſent and ſending of the rightly conſtituted Church, that then was, both the General Aſſemblie and Presbytery.</item>
                  <item>3. That in my Miniſtrie among you, howbeit I came much ſhort of attainment, my reſolution and aime was only to ſet the Glory of God &amp; good of your Souls before mine eyes; &amp; that it pleaſed him ſo to bleſs my poor weak endeavours, as that ſundrie Seals of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie of his Word were viſibly ſeen, ſome whereof are already in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſome are wreſtling thither.</item>
                  <item>4. That when I appeared before the Council, at what time I was ſentenced with baniſhment, for refuſing to ſwear the Oath, as they called it, of Alledgeance, and which was indeed the Oath of Supremacy, and did really contain ſuch a Supremacy, as is ſince fully eſtabliſhed: that then I did not as was propounded by them, take time to adviſe of mine Anſwer, which I judged could import my unclearneſs in the matter; and that it was not ſo much out of reſpect to me, as for that very end propounded; but told plainly, I was fully clear and reſolved not to take it.</item>
               </list> For theſe and many ſuch ſingular paſſages of the Lords gracious guiding me in my Pilgrimage, I deſire from my heart to bleſſe his Glorious Name, and would beg help of all his People to joine with me therein. But
<list>
                  <item>2. I have challenges, beſide many others, in reſpect of theſe particulars, that all along in my Miniſtrie, I did not ſo ſtir up or improve the gift, that the Lord had given me, nor ſo carry my ſelf like a Spiritual, Grave, Diligent and Faithful Serv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant of Chriſt, as I ought to have done.</item>
                  <item>2. That in my Miniſtrie among you, I was not more frequent in viſiting Families, and dealing with Perſons in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, to bring them to and keep them in the wayes of God.</item>
                  <item>3. That when the late grievous defection began in the Year 1661. and 1662. I did not ſtir up my ſelf and others, whatſoever hazard might have enſued, to appear by Supplications and publick Teſtimonies, in avowing the Covenant and work of Reformation, which, if it had been done by Church Judicatories, or but ſingly by Miniſters and Profeſſours, in the due ſeaſon, according to our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, might both have glorified God, been a doore of hope for the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, procured more Peace to our own Conſciences, yea poſſibly ſtopped much of the Defection and Suffering, that hath ſince enſued.</item>
                  <item>4. That when I appeared before the Council, I did not take occaſion humbly, yet plainly, to remonſtrate the guilt of thoſe things, which were publickly enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and done againſt the Prerogative Royal of Jeſus Chriſt, and againſt his Church and People; and to give warning of the wrath to come on them and the Land, without Repentance; but did content my ſelf with anſwering what was propounded to me.</item>
               </list> For theſe and ſuch other neglects and miſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages in my life, I would deſire to go mourning to the grave, and would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat for help from you, and others of the Lords People, to ſeek from Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf pardon, and purifying of both private and publick, both ſins of Perſon and Calling.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:32925:4"/>
            <p n="2">II. As for you, I may reckon you all in three Ranks: The <hi>firſt</hi> Rank, and I fear the greater number, is of thoſe who, although in general profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours of Chriſtianity, yet, ſo far as could be obſerved, never laid Religion to heart; and ſome of theſe for groſſe Ignorance and looſneſs, were alway debarred from the Lords Supper; others although having ſome knowledge and a civil walk, yet upon good grounds were alwayes ſuſpected to be void of the Love and Fear of God, continuing in their natural unrenewed condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neglecting the Worſhip of God in their Families and alone, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by all their carriage that their thoughts and deſires never went beyond this World: Theſe, no doubt, are glad of the change now com'd, that they may caſt off Chriſts yoke, and be free of the Word and Diſcipline, which terrified and tormented them, and may now both ſwear terrible Oaths, and drinke drunk, which by ſome will be expounded as a clear evidence of their loyaltie; they may now, after the example of many Great ones, walk in the luſt of uncleanneſs, mind nothing but how by any means, juſt or unjuſt, to get the World, and then how to ſpend it on their luſts; and hate, and to their power perſecute all, who will not run with them to the ſame exceſs of riot. Now as I have often in publick, with as great earneſtneſs and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as I could, warned theſe to flee from the wrath to come; ſo I would yet deſire them, to ſtand ſtill a little before they go to the pit, and hear from a truely loving Friend a few words, which I am confident, in the day of the great reckoning ſhall be found a meſſage from the living God. Do you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve there is a God, or Heaven or Hell? or can ye with all your will and ſtrength ſcrape the thoughts of theſe out of your ſleeping conſciences? Or do ye in ſuch ſort hate God, that becauſe ye are his creatures, ye will ſo far be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged on your ſelves, as to ſell your ſelves to his enemie, the Devil, for nought, to be tormented in all eternity? I am moſt ſure, none of you all can be ſure that ye are Reprobats; and I can give you aſſurance, greater than the ſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Heaven and Earth, even the ſworn word of him that liveth and reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for ever, that if ye will forſake your wicked way, and yet betake your ſelves to the only Saviour of loſt ſinners, ye are no Reprobates. O! what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage have ye, when ye have gained all the World, and all the Pleaſures, all the Riches, and all the Favoure of it, and have loſt your immortal and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Souls? It is utterly impoſſible, but that ſometimes your own heart tells you, there will be bitterneſs in the end. Doth not Whoredom and Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs waſte the body, take away the Judgment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and leave a ſting in the Conſcience? Can any avoid the Curſe, that goods gotten by falſhood or oppreſſion bring upon the man and all he hath, yea on his Poſterity? Is it not ſad, that Satan can prompt men to Swear, Curſe and Blaſpheme, and utter that which he dare not utter himſelf? And although ye were free of all outward Outbreakings, doth not an unrenewed eſtate, the neglect of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded duties, Sabbath-breaking, and ſuch evils, binde you over to the wrath of Him, who is coming there in flaming fire to take vengeance on them, who know not God, and obey not the Goſpel? Ye may poſſibly think, you reſo far gone on, that there is no retreat, and the wayes of the Lord are ſuch
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32925:4"/>as your diſpoſition can never agree with; but how can your diſpoſition agree to burn &amp; conſume, &amp; never conſume in everlaſting flames, where each of all your fins shall have the own particular torment? How can ye agree to dwell with Internal Furies? Or will ye adde to all your other wickedneſs deſpaire, &amp; deſpiſing of all the Lords loving, loud and long continued Invitations? What shall you anſwer, if hereafter the Lord shall ſay to ſome of you. I would have given thee both Grace and Glory, if thou hadſt but ſough it; thou wouldſt not give once two or three knocks at my door, thou wouldſt not open when I knocked oft and long at thy door; by ſo doing thou haſt ſubſcribed thine own Reprobation and Condemnation. Oh let me obtain this much of all and every one of you, for all the pains I have taken among you in preaching, for all my Nine years banishment from you, for all the prayer I have put up for you, for all the love which he who knoweth all things knoweth I bear to you, yea let your own ſouls, and the love you have to your own welfare here and hereafter obtain it; or rather let him, who for ſinners shed all his moſt precious blood at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> obtain this of you, that you will take one day each of you alone from morne to evening forbearing both meat and drink, and go apart rather into ſome quiet room in an houſe, or unto ſome part of the fields, where you may be moſt quiet, and having before-hand marked in the Bible ſuch Places as are fit to be read at ſuch a time, as alſo having ſomewhat ſearched your way toward God, and his wayes toward you, there ſet yourſelves in his ſight, ſpending the time in Confeſſion of ſins, and Prayer for Pardon and grace to ſerve him, and ſave your own ſouls: and if (which is not readily to be ſuppoſed) ye get no acceſs on ſuch a day, yet continue thereafter in ſuch exerciſe and ſuits; for deliverance from Hell, Enjoying of Heaven and the Favour of God, are worth more pains then ye can take all our Life. Now if this ſo eaſie and neceſſary advice shall be rejected, without preſcribing time and place, or meaſure and manner, but if the main intent of taking ſome time to humble yourſelves before God, and turning unto him be rejected. I take inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, before Son and Moon and all the Creatures, that I have left this warning, as an indorſed ſummones fixed on the doore of your conſciences, to be called and judged before him, who is ready to judge the quick and the dead, at his appearing and in his Glory; when beſide the witneſſing of all your ſins, of your own conſciences<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and of all the Creatures, I alſo, as your lawful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, ſent to procure your Reconciliation with God, shall appear to witneſs that ye got fair warning, but did reject the ſame, and would needs chooſe death. Therefore while it is called to day, take a trial of Chriſts Yoke do but put him to it, and ſee whether or not he will open the windowes of Heaven, and raine Bleſſings and Righteouſneſs upon you; come and ſee, and taſt the goodneſs of the Lord: ye shall be made to ſay, He is a rich and loving Maſter; once engage your hearts to him, and ye may defye Sathan, and all the allurments and terrours of the World, to draw you from him. Glad would my heart be to hear, before I go to the grave, that ſome of you have begun a new courſe, and if ye begin indeed ye will not get it ſuppreſt, it will be heard: I shall as I can pray for it, and deſire others here to pray for it, It is not needful to multiply words, I leave it with you, as ye shall anſwer to Jeſus Chriſt, when he shall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32925:5"/>come in the clouds. The <hi>Second</hi> Rank is of thoſe, who either had true grace or ſeemed to have it, and who went a length beyond others in an orderly walk, and following the Ordinances at home, and abroad, but ſince the late change have either turned looſe and profane, or ſo far ſided with the corruptions of the time, that not one footprint of their former ſtedfaſtneſs &amp; tenderneſs doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, but they are juſtly reckoned among thoſe, who will obey whatſoever is commanded by man, although directly oppoſite to the will of God, revealed in his Word, &amp; to their own lawfully ſworn Engagements. Theſe, without Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance &amp; Amendement, are in a large worſe condition, than thoſe of the <hi>firſt</hi> Rark; for their practice proclameth that once they betook themſelves to Jeſus Chriſt &amp; his wayes, and had ſome love and reſpect for him, but now they repent that ever they did ſo; for they have ſeen ſomething in him, for which they judge, he is not worthie that they should either do or ſuffer any thing for him. I am much aſſured, that Sathan hath got ſuch entrance in ſome of thoſe, who once had a profeſſion, and now are declined, that they shall not again be renewed unto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, but shall wax worſe and worſe, having their conſciences ſeared with an hote yron. Oh that my fears may be prevented! But I have good confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that ſome, who have gone a great length in this courſe of Apoſtacy, shall yet, before they go off the World, glorifie God by a free and full Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their foule fall. Yea, I truſt that ſundrie of them want not a gnawing ſting even all along, but fear of shame before the World, and fear of worldly loſs (and oh how ſmall a thing of the World have any of theſe to have preferred to bleſſed Jeſus Chriſt!) theſe hinder hitherto their coming off their dangerous way. Let all, who have declined, and who have not willingly and wilfully cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to remain in oppoſition to God, and his righteous wayes, and his afflicted People, let them but compare their preſent ſtate with what it was before, and anſwer within their own heart to God, which of the two they allow as beſt? Ye had encouragement beyond many others, in that the Lord enabled three or foure of that Congregation, and theſe but boys, chearfully to endure ſcourging and banishment, rather then depart from their former Principles and Practice, and moſt of theſe are now in a better outward condition, than before: theſe shall be witneſſes againſt you, if ye do not in time betake yourſelves avowedly to your former profeſſion. I have yet by me the Subſcriptions to the Covenant of all the men, that were of the Congregation. Not only that Paper, but the hands of all both men and women, which, in ſwearing the Covenant, after reading the Solemne Acknowledgement of ſins and Engagement to duties, were lifted up to God; theſe hands, becauſe they will endure forever, shall be ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting witneſſes either for you, or againſt you. Ye got warning that ſuch tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als would come, as have ſince enſued, and ſeemed to be fortified againſt them. Remember the ſpeech I had to you, the Monday after the laſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, wherein, preſaging what would shortly follow, I in a manner bid you farewel: ye ſeemed then to be ſomewhat moved, and to reſolve on all hazards to abide by the Cauſe of God; ye ſeemed to run well, who or what hath hindered you, that ye should not obey the truth? It may be there are few or none in all the Land, who in all points have kept their Covenant to God, but have neglected ſome opportunities of their dutie; and the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32925:5"/>good Lord will pardon ſuch, as ſee the plague of their own heart, &amp; turne to him: but to joine in the courſe of defection with thoſe, who have abjured that Covenant; to countenance an intruded Hireling, and join with him in that which they call Worship, yea to ſit and drink with him, who was lawfully and deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly Excommunicated by the Church of Scotland; to keep Holy Dayes appointed by men; to withdraw from the fellowship and meetings of thoſe, who in ſome degree continue in their integrity; theſe are ſuch groſs and direct violations of the Oath of God, as can proceed from nothing but a fearful deſerting of God; from a preferring the will of man, to the will of the living God, and preferring the eaſe and petty pelf of the world to the Salvation of your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſouls. I am fully ſure, ye dare not ſay before the Lord, that although all feat of inconvenience from man were quite taken away, yet conſcience of obeying the will of God would make you do, as now ye do If ye were ſure within ten dayes by death to turn your back on all, would ye not think it fitting, that both God and the world ſaw a change on you, from your preſent way? and ye have no aſſurance of one day. Think often on Chriſts Word, that <hi>who deny him before men, he will deny them before his Father.</hi> It is impoſſible, it is utterly impoſſible, to be a Diſciple of Jeſus Chriſt, or an heir of glory, without a Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to quite all, even Life it ſelf, for his ſake, when called to it. I am much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayed, when the conſcience of ſome of you shall waken, that ye shall hardly be keeped from ſome degrees of deſpair. Come off, come off in time, be not afrayed or ashamed to witneſs againſt yourſelves, and the wicked courſe of the time; give Glory to God get peace to your own conſciences, ſtrengthen the hands, and make glad the hearts of thoſe, that are ſeeking God; ye know not but if ye delay, your wakening may come after the door is shut, and that then shall be no times of refreshing from the preſence of the Lord, As for the poor wretch, that is thruſt-in upon you do not hate him, do not injure him, rather pray for him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e means, if it be poſſible, that he may recover; but do not countenance or join with him; ye may eaſily be ſenſible, he is not a meſſenger from the Lord, for your ſpiritual good, but a ſnare and hardener of you in unwarranted wayes. I may by good ground from the Word of God affirm, that unleſs a gracious change be wrought, both he and all that follow him shall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish Eternally. Now the Lord himſelf, who only can do it, open your eyes to ſee the danger of your way, urge and enable you to take ſometime to mourn before him in ſecret, and openly to teſtify, as occaſion offers, before good and evil, that ye are returned to your former Profeſſion; then shall none of all your Tranſgreſſions be mentioned unto you.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Third</hi> Rank is the little handful of thoſe, who in ſuch an evil time have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to keep their garments clean, to whom it is given in the behalf of Chriſt, nor only to beleeve on him, but alſo to ſuffer, or at leaſt expoſe themſelves to ſuffering for his ſake: ye have great cauſe to bleſs the Lord, &amp; I and many others will joine with you, to bleſs his holy name, that howbeit ye have but a little ſtrength, ye deſire to keep his word, and not deny his name; ye have found and will finde yet more, that Chriſt will not be behinde with you, nor ſleep in your debt. I truſt your conſolations abound, far beyond your fears or dangers or ſufferings, your hundred fold is going to the fore for you and yours, in the Bank
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32925:6"/>of Heaven, when more than an hundred is the intereſt for one. Chriſt was once owned as King of his Church, in that Land, that in Doctrine, Worship, Diſcipline and Government, his Lawes in his Word should be the only Rule; and hereunto all from the higheſt to the loweſt had by Oath engaged themſelves; now abjured Prelacy is brought in, Chriſts faithful ſervants caſt out, hirelings thruſt-in in his houſe, the whole diſpoſing of Church Matters, Perſons and Meetings by the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Supremacy,</hi> referr'd to the ſole arbitriment of a mortal Creature, &amp; Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution bended againſt all, who go not alongs in that Apoſtacy &amp; Perjury: &amp; is not then ſuffering ſtated on as important a quarrel, as ever was ſince the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world? the ſmalleſt point of Chriſts Prerogative royal, is not only worth the ſufferings, but worth more than the Eternal Salvation of all the Elect. Be not afraid but he, who ſits crowned King on mount Zion, knows well how to right himſelf; not onl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a touch of the iron rod in his hand, or the ſword that cometh out of his mouth, but a frown or wink of his eye, can dash in pieces all the potsheards of the Earth: He shall appear to your joy, and they shall be ashamed; this cloud of Oppoſition to his worke will be ſcattered, as many others have been before. He is only taking a trial, what will be every mans part; and not only the malice of Enemies, but the weakneſs of ſome of his own will be diſcovered. He will ſuffer the Oppoſers of his worke to ſport themſelves a little, as if they had don their work, &amp; rooted out both truth and godlineſs; &amp; he will have his own brought to a neceſſity both of more vigorous faith depending cleanly &amp; cloſſe on himſelf and his word, and more deep humiliation, ſerious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and amendement: but he hath his ſet time, when he will awake as a mighty man; &amp;, I hope, build his Palace in that Land, with the addition of more glory, than ever was before. As for you, I would advertiſe you of two or three things.
<list>
                  <item>1. It is not enough to be ſtedfaſt in the preſent controverſie, ye muſt ſtudy to be Holy in all manner of converſation, and shine as lights, blameleſs and harmleſs, the Sons of God, without rebuke in the mids of a crooked and perverſe nation: an idol entertained in the heart, or a blemish in the life will make a fearful diſcovery of unſoundneſs in the end: let the love and fear of God be made evident to all onlookers, in all your carriage; ſo shall ye go neer to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince even Adverſaries of the reality of your Religion.</item>
                  <item>2. Conſider, this battel is not at an end, ye have not reſiſted unto blood, ye know not what trials may abide you, keep on your armour, ſtrengthen your reſolution to deny yourſelves, and all ye have, for his ſake; dwell neer to and be alwayes in good terms with the Captain of Salvation, and be not afraid but ye shall be fournished abundantly what to ſay, what to do, and how to endure.</item>
                  <item>3. If the Lord, for ſuch fearful Apoſtacy, and Breach of Covenant, shall beſides the dreadful ſpiritual Judgements already poured out, ſend any common Calamity in that Land, as Sword, Peſt or Famine, I would pray and hope, that ye may be hid: but if any of theſe ſtrokes shall reach any of you, do not grudge, your ſins might procure more; it is much if ye get your ſouls for a prey.</item>
                  <item>4. Keep up your meetings for prayer and mutual upſtirring, cry mightily to God, each of you apart; ſo shall not your meetings be flat or formal: a few wreſtlers may help to keep God in the Land, he is not willing to depart, if any will but hold him. Seek repentance to the Land and yourſelves, ſtability to thoſe that ſtand,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32925:6"/>recovery to ſuch as have ſliden or fallen: let me have ſome little ſhare in your prayers, that I may finiſh my courſe with joy, and ſtill bring forth fruit in old age. Seek from the Lord light Zeal, Wiſdome and Tenderneſs, to deal with any of your neighbours, that ever appeared for him, &amp; now have declined: if ye prevail with any of them, admit them to your meetings.</item>
               </list> Even the Lord give you underſtanding in all things.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Now as concerning the Condition of the Church, and Work of God in that Land, ye remember, that although I ſhuned not, according to my poor meaſure, and as occaſion offered, and neceſſity required, to ſhew my minde of publick Matters, Dangers and Duties of the time; yet I uſed not to inſiſt very much in ſuch things, as not being much inclined or able for diſputing; and having found by frequent experience, that ſo ſoon as any were gained to cloſe indeed with Chriſt, and lay Religion to heart in earneſt, theſe generally out of a native principle became preſently ſound in the controverſies of the time. And in the preſent caſe, ſeveral things would rather ſeem to perſwade ſilence, becauſe indeed our preſent Condition ought rather to be matter of lamentation and mourning before the Lord, day and night, alone and in company, then matter of diſcourſe amongſt ourſelves; and becauſe it is very hard to uſe freedome, and not diſpleaſe ſome, whom a man would be very unwilling to offend; and becauſe of all men living, I have leaſt reaſon to think, that I would offer my light as a rule of any other mans light. But when I conſider that as one (although moſt unworthie, yet) intruſted by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, as an Ambaſſadour from him to his people, I am ſhortly to give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count before him of my negotiation, I cannot decline what light, I judge, I have from him out of his word, anent preſent affairs, to open the ſame to you, as in his ſight, in as great ſimplicity and ingenuity, as I can.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Firſt,</hi> I need not inſiſt to declare, that notwithſtanding of all, that hath fallen out of late, and all the Objections againſt the Work of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, all which were both propounded and anſwered above 30. years ago, that yet both I &amp; all that Land, &amp; the poſterity after us ſtand bound before the Lord, to adhere to the National Covenant, the Solemn League and Covenant, and all the parts and degrees of Reformation and Uniformity, which we had attained: neither will I conceal, that howbeit thereafter I withdrew from the meetings of the Proteſters, when I perceived the matter like to tend to a ſtated Schiſme; that yet after as narrow ſearch, as I could make, I have no Challenges, but rather Approbation, that in the beginning I joined in the Proteſtation, againſt the courſes taken in the year 1651. and thereafter, for bringing in the Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Enemies of the Work of God, to Counſels and Command. I am not willing to take in ſuch aſhes (Oh if the fire were extinguiſhed and forgotten!) and I know that ſome good men, in a day of great darkneſs and diſtreſs, did what they conceived for the time dutie; yet when I conſider our former en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagments to the contrair, and that the principles and motives of theſe courſes would neceſſarily recoil againſt former endeavours of purging the army; &amp; againſt the Oppoſition made to the unlawful Engagement in the year 1648. yea againſt the Solemn League and Covenant; and by conſequence againſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32925:7"/>the late work of Reformation, yea againſt the firſt Reformation from Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery; and that the bulk of the diſaffected Miniſters of the Land, ſome where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, although born down, might have been obſerved in every General Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, even from the year 1638. that theſe did natively joyn to make up the party, I judge theſe courſes to have been no ſmall ſtep of the defection of the Church. I could have wiſhed indeed, that more moderation, &amp; more real endeavours for union in the Lord, had been uſed on both ſides; but I was alſo convinced, that the late ſad change was in ſome reſpect ſeaſonably ſent from the Lord, that faithful Miniſters and Profeſſours ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuffer by the Prelats, and ſuch as by overturning the Work of God, brought them in, than by Judicatours of the Church, which in all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance would ſhortly have followed; yea in ſome places was already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun: And it is moſt ſad, that when time hath brought to light the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conſequence of theſe courſes, yet few or none of theſe have te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified any reſentment thereof. Beſide clear Demonſtrations of the Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of the Goſpel, in converting and confirming ſinners, which hath been as conſpicuous in the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as in any of the Reformed Churches, the Lord was pleaſed from the beginning to put in the hand of his Servants, in that Land, apiece of Service, not ſo directly called-for at the hands of ſame others of the Churches, to wit, as Chriſt's Prophetical &amp; Prieſtly Office had been debated, ſuffered-for and cleared; ſo they ſhould ſtand and contend for his Kingly Office; that he is not only inwardly a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Head to his Myſtical Church; but externally a Spiritual Politick Head to the Politick Body of the viſible Church of Profeſſours, &amp; their only Law-giver; to inveſt them with intrinſick power to meet for his Worſhip; and their Officers appointed by him, to meet for Diſcipline &amp; Ordering the affairs of his houſe; that no Ceremonie or Invention of man, that want his ſtamp, is to be brought into his Worſhip; no Officer to be brought into his houſe, but ſuch as he hath appointed in his Word; &amp; although his ſervants, &amp; people are to carry towards Gods Ordinance of Magiſtracy, where they live, as any other Subjects, &amp; to deny them no reſpect or obedience, due to them; yet in their Meetings &amp; Adminiſtrations they are not ſubordinat unto or dependant on any Civil power. Theſe and ſuch others were the points aſſerted, and ſuffered for by the renowed worthies of this Church, by <hi>Mr Knox, Mr Welſh, Mr Bruce</hi> and many others, who now ſhine in glory. And although there have been in former times, ſeveral ſad dayes of the defection of Miniſters, as in the year 1584 and at other times, yet becauſe there never was ſuch a black houre and power of darkneſs, as is now fallen upon us. I ſhall in the ſecond place touch ſome particulars. for which I judge ye, and I, and many others have reaſon moſt bitterly to mourn before the Lord. I. That in the beginning of this grievous defection. ſuch a baſe cowardiſe fell generally on all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that not one Teſtimony from any Church Judicatory in <hi>Scotland,</hi> was given to the cauſe of God, and againſt the horrid violation of a ſworn Covenant; yea ſome as induſtriouſly ſtopped Teſtimonies, as if they had been hired ſo to do; ſome whereof pretending, it was not a fit time, when a moſt fit time came, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32925:7"/>being urged thereto by Authority, yet declined it. It was firſt and laſt the guilt of thoſe, who had the conviction on them, to neglect the duty, for want of the concurrence of others. True Zeal for the honour of our Maſter, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of our reckoning before him, would have ſtirred us up to another ſort of boldneſs: we would not have been ſo blunt in our own concernment: the ſight of the Fathers danger brake the tack of a Son's tongue, who was tongue-tacked from the birth. The Lord indeed provided a real Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony from ſome, who had and have yet of their bones witneſſing before the ſun. But oh that we did not adventure ſomewhat for his glory, for our own peace, for the good of Poſterity, yea for the true good and edifying even of our Oppoſites! We ought not only to be deeply humbled, and deal much and long for pardon of ſuch an Omiſſion; but earneſtly ſeek grace and ſtrength to take hold of any opportunity for reparing ſuch a loſs. 2. That ſome of thoſe Miniſters, who were laid aſide by Authority, did in a manner lay themſelves aſide, as if they had been exonered of all Charge; whereas ſuch as have any liberty of a Subject, and feet and tongue looſe, ought rather be inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, and from houſe to houſe inſtruct and warn young and old both of former Charge, and every where, as occaſion offers: It is true, none are now Apoſtles, but Miniſters have the ſame charge, that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles had, to feed the Flock of Chriſt, and are given primarily not to any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Charge, but to the Univerſal viſible Church: few of the Apoſtles, or Apoſtolick Men, had either ſuch Churches and Pulpits to preach in, or a ſetled maintenance. Love to Chriſt, and love to the ſouls of People, that are periſhing in ignorance and diſobedience, would baniſh the love of eaſe, and the fear of danger, and the idol of carnal prudence. That however a man, for maintenance of himſelf, and his family, might practiſe medicine, or labour land, or betake himſelf to any other employment; yet he is to remember the miniſtrie is his main imployment, and that at his admiſſion he engadged befor God to be diligent and faithful therein. Some have preached out of priſon windowes; ſome have converted their keepers: It were to be wiſhed, that a Miniſter in all places, in all company, at all times, were about ſomewhat of his Maſters work; ſo ſhall he hear at laſt, well done good and faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. Let us deal with the Lord, that he will deal with the hearts of all his Servants, and thruſt them out into his harveſt; as I hope ſome, who ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be ſomewhat deficient in that duty, are already begun to beſtir themſelves; and others, upon ſight of the courſes of the time, and the peoples neceſſity and willingneſs to hear, will do yet more abundantly.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That after the deſtroyers of the Lords heritage, had razed the work of Reformation to the foundation, and had not only invaded the rights that he hath allowed this Servants, in the Government of his houſe, but, as far as creatures can do, uſurped his own Prerogative Royal; and not at all hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſnare, but by the letter to the Council, and the Councels Act open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the deſigne, to have the Miniſtrie of the Word wholly dependant on the Civil Power and Supremacy; that yet ſome Miniſters accepted that, which they called an Indulgence of their Miniſtrie, without any publick teſtimony,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32925:8"/>either of their adherence to the Oath of God and work of Reformation, or againſt theſe Uſurpations. Oh for a head turned into waters, &amp; eyes a fountain of tears, to deplore day &amp; night ſuch an indignity, done to the Son of God, without a witneſs; and ſuch ſhame caſt upon the Church of Scotland. Our Fathers for far leſs matters conteſted with the Powers of the earth, that the truth of the Goſpel might continue with us; and do we think that our Lord and Maſter is not able to maintain his own cauſe? I have great charity for moſt of the men, who I ſuppoſe may have a ſting in the boſome, for neglect of the opportunity. A <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; a <hi>Barnabas</hi> may be carried away at a time to and by a diſſimulation: the credit of the Miniſtrie ought to be dear to us, but the credite of our Maſter and His intereſts ought to be dearer then all things elſe. The Miniſtrie of the Goſpel is indeed a great benefite, but nothing hinders why the Miniſtrie of the Goſpel might not have heen had, and may not yet be had without a Pulpit and a Stipend; It is an ill made bargan, where the one party gets clear gain, the keyes of Chriſts houſe in a manner deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered up to them; and the other is uncertain if God will bleſs a Miniſtrie, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed at ſuch a rate. If any Miniſters have had a hand in contriving or procuring that Indulgence, I ſuppoſe, they have done more miſchief to the poor Church of Chriſt in that Land, then all the Prelats, and all their Hirelings; and if ſuch an Indulgence ſhould be offered to, and accepted by all the outed Miniſters of the Land, without a publick teſtimony, I would look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as the moſt dreadful preſage, that yet hath appeared, of the Lords totale forſaking of the Land, It is not now Epiſcopacy and Ceremonies, that is the Controverſie; but whether Jeſus Chriſt be King of his own Church, which He hath bought with His Bloud; or if the Leviathan of the Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy ſhall ſwallow up all, to which it is all alike whether it have Prelats or Presbyters ſubſervient unto it, onely it muſt rule according to its own arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment without control, and bring forth yet more and more fruits of all impiety and profanity. A Miniſter, that can preach truths, which no man que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, &amp; miskens this grand controverſie, or ſpeaks of it ſo darkly, as that he diſcovers he deſires not to be underſtood; I durſt not ſay, that in that he is a faithful Ambaſſadour of Jeſus Chriſt. Sure, if his own reputation were touched, he would ſpeake in a more picquant manner; and his Maſters honour ſhould be above his own repute. A bare not agreeing to the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation propounded is not a ſufficient evidence of faithfulneſs, at ſuch a time. Sathan counts no great gain of the Prelats, nor them that ſet them up, nor them that follow them; but outed Miniſters and noted Profeſſours would be a great prize to him: and I am ſure, winnow as hard as he can, he ſhall get none that belong unto Chriſt. O how ſad is it that ſome to pleaſe men, and thoſe the overturners of all the work of God, have laid aſide that uſeful part of Reformation and Uniformity, the expounding of the Scripture, formerly practiſed to ſo much edification, &amp; others magle it ſo, as it were as good to forbear it. The excuſe of the ſhort dayes of winter, or the weakneſs of ones body, may well allow a man to make both the Lecture &amp; the Preaching ſhorter, but on ſuch a pretext to lay it aſide, eſpecially, being in ſome ſort
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32925:8"/>a caſe of confeſſion, I fear ſhall not be allowed before the righteous Judge. If it be ſaid, better have preaching without Lecturing, nor no preaching at all. True, if there be a Phyſical impediment in the way of lecturing, or if all preaching had been by the Lord aſtricted to ſuch a pulpit by the indulgence of ſuch a creature: but when men come to ſpy out our liberty, which we have in Chriſt Jeſus, that they may bring us into bondage, and would inure us to take one of their burdens after another, we ought not to give place by ſubjection, no not for an houre; for by ſuch arguing, better have preaching without ever citing <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> nor none; better without mentioning the decree of election, or imputed righteouſneſs, nor none at all. Alas! the Lord hath poured on us the Spirit of deep ſleep, and hath cloſed our eyes, our Prophets and our Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, the Seers hath he covered. O what a deep wound was it to my heart, to hear of a Miniſter, who I think certainly hath both true grace and rare gifts, that he ſo far complied with the courſe of the time, as to keep a holy Day, appointed by men, and drink about the Bone-fires! what will be the end of thoſe things? What, when God ſhall waken the Conſcience? Our Miniſters were our Glory, and I fear our Idol, and the Lord hath ſtained the pride of our glory. None of us who are here, and ſeem to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfyed with ſome things at home want conviction of our own grievous miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages; and it is probable that if we had been at home, we might have done worſe than any others. If it were poſſible, I would deſire ſo to ſpeake for Chriſt and his intereſt, as not to reflect on any Perſon, but <hi>Levi's</hi> dutie and bleſſing lies otherwayes. I profeſſe to you, although I have a real excuſe of my inability to debate and argue, without which the propounding of ones minde ſeemes too Dictator like, that yet I have apprehenſion, that my not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſome friends, makes the guilt of ſomethings done or omitted more mine than theirs. Oh for the day, when all of us, whether together or apart, without reflecting on any but ourſelves, might mourn the mourning of Had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drimmon, in the Valley of Megiddon, I ſhould look on that, as Scotlands great delivery: yea it is to be moſt earneſtly ſought from the Lord, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the whole bulk of the people, and even thoſe who have car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on the defection, might get repentance; ſo ſhould we be a greater wonder to the world of his matchleſs mercy, nor now we are of ſudden and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Apoſtacy: and many ſuch wonders he can work; if he pleaſe, and we may ſuppoſe will work, if there were wreſtlers for ſuch a bleſſing, but that alſo is his own gift: to him be all glory for ever.</p>
            <p>In the cloſe, it will be expected that I give you all ſome directions, how to walk in ſuch a time; and as they come in my mind, I shall ſet them down.
<list>
                  <item>1. In all things, and above all things, let the Word of God be your only Rule, Chriſt Jeſus your only hope, His Spirit your only Guide, and His Glory your only End.</item>
                  <item>2. See that each of you apart Worship God every day, morning &amp; evening, at leaſt; read ſome of His Word, and call on Him by prayer, and give Him thanks, if ye be ſtraitned with buſineſs, it is not ſo much the length of your Prayer that he regards, as the Uprightneſs &amp; the Earneſtneſ of the heart; but neglect not the dutie; and if ye be without the hearing of others, utter your voice, it is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32925:9"/>ſometime a great help, but do it not to be heard of others; ſing alſo a Pſalme, or ſome part of a Pſalme; ye may learne ſome by heart for that purpoſe.</item>
                  <item>3. Through the whole day labour to ſet the Lord alwayes before you, as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to obſerve you, and ſtrengthen you for every dutie, and then look over how the day hath been ſpent, before ye ſleep.</item>
                  <item>4. Such as have Families ſet up the Worship of God in your Families, as ye would avoid the wrath, that shall be poured on the Families that call not on his name.</item>
                  <item>5. As occaſion offers of any honeſt Miniſter coming alongs, neglect not the ſame; and on the Lords Day, go where ye can hear the Word ſincerly preached by a ſent Miniſter, who will witneſs againſt the evils of the time, without which, I apprehend, wharever a mans gifts be, the Lord will not ſend the bleſſing. <hi>Oxnam</hi> is not far off, and I hope <hi>Mr Scot</hi> doth, and will declare for the ſworn Reformation, and teſtify a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the preſent defection; but I dar not bid you hear any of the intruded Hirelings, whom they call Curats. I know ſome good men have heard, or do hear ſome of them, but I believe, if all fear of inconvenience were removed, they would do otherwayes. If no occaſion of a publick meeting be, or if ye cannot go to it, ſanctifie the Lords Day in your Families, or at leaſt each of you in your own heart.</item>
                  <item>6. Give no occaſion to the World to ſay, that ye neglect your Calling, or are buſie bodies in other mens matters, or have any doublneſs in your worldly dealings, a faithful carriage free of covetouſneſs is a great orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the profeſſion.</item>
                  <item>7. Have a care of your Children that they be taught to read, and have Bibles ſo ſoon as they can uſe them, and take them with you to hear the Word preached, and inſtruct them your ſelves the more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, that publick means are ſcarce.</item>
                  <item>8. Such as have any leaſure, read ſome good Books, whereby ye may profite in knowledge and affection: read now and then the Covenants, the Confeſſion of Faith, and the longer Catechiſme, and the little Treatiſe printed with them. I would recommend to you the writings of <hi>Mr Durham,</hi> and <hi>Mr Binning,</hi> and <hi>Mr William Gutrie,</hi> and <hi>Mr An drew Gray,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Mr Rutherford's</hi> Letters, (I hope shortly ye shall be ſupplied with ſome more Copies of them) as alſo any good pieces from England, as <hi>Mr Allen,</hi> or the like: I dar not recommend <hi>Baxter</hi> to you, he is a dangerous Man: let <hi>Chaſters</hi> and <hi>Standhil</hi> buy ſome ſuch as they oan, and lend them to others to be read.</item>
                  <item>9. Any thoughts ye have of the buſineſs of the time, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine them well by the word, and preſent them oft to God by prayer; and what ye get ſo confirmed, be not eaſily moved therefrom, although ſome Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters should be of a contrair opinion; for in thoſe dayes ſundrie of the common People have clearer light and ſteadier practice, than ſome Miniſters; but be not proud, or ſelf willed in your own opinion.</item>
                  <item>10 By any means ſee that ye be not drawn to a contempt of the Miniſtrie, or Miniſters in whom any thing of God really appeareth, although ſome might have ſliden in an houre of temptation; but ſtudy all lawful wayes of union and healing, yet ſo as ye approve nothing, which the word and your conſcience condemne.</item>
                  <item>11. Strengthen your ſelves in the main grounds of Religion againſt Popery, and read ſome short treatiſes for that purpoſe; ye know not but it may be a great part of the trial of the time.</item>
                  <item>12. Some Miniſters have begun of late to queſtion Chriſts imputed righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, look upontheſe, whatever shew they may make of moderation and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curat,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32925:9"/>walking, as enemies to Jeſus Chriſt and the ſalvation of ſouls.</item>
                  <item>13. Keep you far, very far, from this laſt device of Satans, Quakeriſme, which, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of ſobriety and patience, overthrows all the grounds of Chriſtian Religion; and indeed they should not be looked-on as Chriſtians; themſelves and the light within them, which is alſo in all Pagans, is all their Saviour: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe not with them: as much as ye can, avoid conference with them; the evil Spirit that is in them deſires no better, nor continual wrangling: many are much miſtaken if there be not much Devilry among them, as ſome com'd off from them have teſtified.</item>
                  <item>14. I know the courſe ceaſeth now that was taken, for providing the poore with meat, but after your ability ſet apart ſome of your means for the poore; I mean not the ſturdie Vagabonds, but poor Houshol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, eſpecially thoſe that have any good in them.</item>
                  <item>13. Deal in all earneſtneſs and love with any of your Neighbours, whom ye perceive in a way that will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their ſouls: viſite your Neighbours in their ſickneſs, and drop ſomething for their ſouls good</item>
                  <item>16. Let ſuch as have been Elders, and have not run the wicked courſe of the time, know that their obligation ceaſeth not, but rather is increaſed to viſite and overſee the Flock, and warn and comfort, as occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.</item>
                  <item>17. Forget not Chriſts Command to love your Enemies, and pray for them that perſecute you: many a time our carnal anger and bitterneſs puts on a diſguiſe, as if it were zeal; true love to God and our Neighbour would prompt us to many duties, that now are forgot, and to a better way of doing duties, and yet keep us from being partakers of other mens ſins.</item>
                  <item>18. Guard your hearts from a carnal diſpoſition, in ſpeaking or hearing of the miſcarriages of others, and let not that be all the matter of your diſcourſe, howbeit it may be part; but there is more edifying to be ſpeaking of what is good.</item>
                  <item>19. I hear there is a rare work of grace begun of late in ſome, not far from you, in the borders of Northumberland, I judge it were for your advantage if ſome of you, ſuch as are able, went thither to be acquainted with them: your Friend <hi>Henry Hall</hi> would eaſily make your acquaintance: their fire edge might help to kindle-up old ſitten-up profeſſours; yea if ſome of you who are yet graceleſs would go &amp; ſee their way, they might be ſmitted with that bleſſed diſeaſe.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I fear ye shall hardly read my hand, and yet it hath taken neerby as many dayes to write, as there are pages; but it was not fitting to make uſe of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hand.</p>
            <p>Let this Letter be read to all of the Parish, who will be willing to hear it; and to any that are gon out of it, as <hi>Andrew Burkholme</hi> and <hi>Margaret Walker,</hi> or any that uſed ordinarily to meet with us, as <hi>Mrs Eliot, Iſabel Simpſon,</hi> and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. I know there is a great change, ſince I left you, by the death of ſome, and coming in of others but I am ſometime refreshed to look over the roll of the Parish, as it was when I left you. Deſire from me <hi>Mr Henry</hi> and <hi>Mr William Erskin,</hi> or any other of that ſort, to come now and then to viſite and water you. I could wiſh that when ye hear of any honeſt Merchant in <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> or any other coming hither, ſome of you would give them a particular account of both good and evil, to bring to me; I had a little account lately from <hi>John Tetcha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that made me both joyful and ſad; I ſhall write when any of my Sons are to come over, that if they can, they will come to you, a day or two, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32925:10"/>bring me information how it is with you. Now as I oan at this diſtance, I em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace you all, and all that uſed to join with us at our Communions: I ſalute you all. I bleſs you all, I commend you all to God and the Word of His Grace, which is able to build you up, and give you an inheritance among all them which are ſanctified. The rich and powerful Grace of the Lord JESUS CHRIST be with you all. Thus wiſheth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving and lawful Paſtor JOHN LIVINGSTOUN.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Rotterdam</hi> 
                  <date>7. <hi>October</hi> 1671.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:32925:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
